<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">

<chapter id="jca-intro.chapt">
  <title>JCA Introduction</title>
  <section id="jca_introduce">
   <title>JCA Overview</title>
    
   <para>The Java Connector Architecture (JCA) defines a standard architecture for connecting
     the Java EE platform to heterogeneous Enterprise Information Systems (EIS). 
     Examples of EISs include Enterprise Resource Planning (ERP), mainframe transaction processing (TP), 
     databases and messaging systems.</para>

   <para>The connector architecture defines a set of scalable, secure, and transactional
     mechanisms that enable the integration of EISs with application servers and
     enterprise applications.</para>
    
   <para>The connector architecture also defines a Common Client Interface (CCI) for EIS
     access. The CCI defines a client API for interacting with heterogeneous EISs.</para>

   <para>The connector architecture enables an EIS vendor to provide a standard resource
     adapter for its EIS. A resource adapter is a system-level software driver that is used
     by a Java application to connect to an EIS. The resource adapter plugs into an
     application server and provides connectivity between the EIS, the application server,
     and the enterprise application. The resource adapter serves as a protocol adapter
     that allows any arbitrary EIS communication protocol to be used for connectivity.
     An application server vendor extends its system once to support the connector
     architecture and is then assured of seamless connectivity to multiple EISs. Likewise,
     an EIS vendor provides one standard resource adapter which has the capability to
     plug in to any application server that supports the connector architecture.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="jca_whatsnew">
    <title>What's New</title>

    <para>New feature:</para>
    <itemizedlist spacing="compact">
      <listitem>
        How the JCA layer registers XA datasource for XA Resource Recovery with the JBoss TS project. See
<xref linkend="XARecoveryinJCA" />.
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
</chapter>

